大家好 我是凯莉·安 欢迎来到计算机科学速成课
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne, and welcome to Crash Course Computer Science!
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
关于排序我们说过不少
So we've talked a lot about sorting in this series
通常排序一列数的代码只有十行
and often code to sort a list of numbers might only be ten lines long,
对一个程序员来说很简单
which is easy enough for a single programmer to write.
另外 它足够短不需要特殊的工具
Plus, it's short enough that you don't need any special tools
你用记事本就能写
- you could do it in Notepad. Really!
但是 一个排序算法并不是一个程序
But, a sorting algorithm isn't a program;
它只可能是一个更大的程序的一个小部分
it's likely only a small part of a much larger program.
比如 微软的Office有大约4千万行代码
For example, Microsoft Office has roughly 40 millions lines of code.
4千万！
40 MILLION!
它远大于一个人能思考和工作
That's way too big for any one person to figure out and write!
搭建这样庞大的程序 程序员有一系列工具和惯例
To build huge programs like this, programmers use a set of tools and practices.
合在一起形成了软件编程的规范
Taken together, these form the discipline of Software Engineering
玛格丽特·汉密尔顿创造了这个术语
- a term coined by engineer Margaret Hamilton,
她在阿波罗登月计划中帮NASA防止了许多严重的问题
who helped NASA prevent serious problems on the Apollo mission to the moon.
她曾经这样解释 这就像等到最后一刻进行牙根管手术
She once explained it this way: 'It's kind of like a root canal: you waited till the end
但是明明可以提前养成好习惯
but there are things you could have done beforehand.
就像是预防治疗 不过这是预防软件
It's like preventative health care, but it's preventative software.'
12集说到的 将大项目分解为小的功能
As I mentioned in episode 12, breaking big programs into smaller functions
可以让很多人同时工作
allows many people to work simultaneously.
他们不需要对全部程序操心 只负责他们做的那个函数
They don't have to worry about the whole thing, just the function they're working on.
所以如果你的任务是写排序算法
So, if you're tasked with writing a sort algorithm,
你只要保证排序正确和高效
you only need to make sure it sorts properly and efficiently.
不过 仅仅把代码包装进函数并不够
However, even packing code up into functions isn't enough.
微软Office可能有成百上千的函数
Microsoft Office probably contains hundreds of thousands of them.
这比直接处理4千万行代码要好
That's better than dealing with 40 million lines of code,
但仍对一个人或一个团队而言太大了
but it's still way too many ‘things’ for one person or team to manage.
解决办法是把函数包装进层次结构
The solution is to package functions into hierarchies,
把相关联的代码放一起形成 对象
pulling related code together into 'objects'.
例如 汽车的软件可能有几个巡航控制相关的函数
For example, car's software might have several functions related to cruise control,
像是设置速度 加速或减速 停止巡航控制的一系列功能
like setting speed, nudging speed up or down, and stopping cruise control altogether.
既然它们都相关联 我们可以把它们包装在一起形成统一巡航控制对象
Since they're all related, we can wrap them up into a unified cruise control object.
但是我们不停留于此 巡航控制只是引擎软件的一部分
But, we don't have to stop there, cruise control is just one part of the engine's software.
还有函数组用于控制
There might also be sets of functions that control
火花塞点火 进油 水箱
spark plug ignition, fuel pumps, and the radiator.
所以我们可以创造一个父对象包含这些子对象 即引擎对象
So we can create a 'parent' Engine Object that contains all of these 'children' objects.
子对象之外 引擎自身也会有函数
In addition to children objects, the engine itself might have its own functions.
例如停止和启动
You want to be able to stop and start it, for example.
它还有自身的变量 像是行驶里程
It'll also have its own variables, like how many miles the car has traveled.
总之 对象可以包含其他对象 函数和变量
In general, objects can contain other objects, functions and variables.
当然 引擎也只是汽车对象的一部分
And of course, the engine is just one part of a Car Object.
还有传动系统 车轮 车门 车窗等等
There's also the transmission, wheels, doors, windows, and so on.
作为程序员 我如果想设置巡航控制
Now, as a programmer, if I want to set the cruise control,
我向下浏览对象层级
I navigate down the object hierarchy,
从最外层的对象到深入嵌套的对象
from the outermost objects to more and more deeply nested ones.
最终找到我要触发的函数
Eventually, I reach the function I want to trigger:
先是汽车 然后引擎 再巡航控制 最后设置巡航速度为55
'Car, then engine, then cruise control, then set cruise speed to 55'.
编程语言经常使用图示相似的句法
Programming languages often use something equivalent to the syntax shown here.
将功能单元包装成嵌套的对象的思想叫做
The idea of packing up functional units into nested objects is called
面向对象的编程
Object Oriented Programming.
它和我们所有集数的做法很相似
This is very similar to what we've done all series long:
通过封装低级的细节在高级组件中降低复杂度
hide complexity by encapsulating low-level details in higher-order components.
之前我们把晶体管电路封装成高级的布尔逻辑门
Before we packed up things like transistor circuits into higher-level boolean gates.
现在对软件同样如此
Now we're doing the same thing with software.
再一次 进入新一层的抽象
Yet again, it's a way to move up a new level of abstraction!
把大的程序如汽车软件分解为
Breaking up a big program, like a car's software,
函数单元完美适合团队
into functional units is perfect for teams.
一个团队负责巡航控制系统
One team might be responsible for the cruise control system,
这个团队的其中一个程序员处理几个函数
and a single programmer on that team tackles a handful of functions.
这就像巨大的实体如摩天大楼的建造过程
This is similar to how big, physical things are built, like skyscrapers.
有电工搭设电线 水管工安装管道 焊工进行焊接
You'll have electricians running wires, plumbers fitting pipes, welders welding,
油漆工粉刷 以及数百人分散在外墙周围
painters painting, and hundreds of other people teeming all over the hull.
他们同时在不同的部分工作 运用各自不同的技能
They work together on different parts simultaneously, leveraging their different skills.
直到某天建成一整个建筑
Until one day, you've got a whole working building!
不过回到巡航控制的例子 它的代码
But, returning to our cruise control example. Its code is going to have to
会用到引擎软件其他部分的函数
make use of functions in other parts of the engine's software,
来保持汽车的匀速
to, you know, keep the car at a constant speed.
那段代码不是巡航控制团队的任务
That code isn't part of the cruise control team's responsibility.
是另一个团队的
It's another team's code.
因为巡航控制团队没有写那段代码
Because the cruise control team didn't write that,
所以他们需要好的文件说明解释代码中每个函数干什么
they're going to need good documentation about what each function in the code does,
以及定义良好的应用程序编程接口API
and a well-defined Application Programming Interface - or API for short.
你可以把API想象成合作的程序员
You can think of an API as the way that collaborating programmers
在代码不同部分间互动的通道
interact across various parts of the code.
例如点火控制对象
For example, in the IgnitionControl object,
里面有函数设置引擎的每分钟转速
there might be functions to set the RPM of the engine,
检查火花塞电压 和点燃单个火花塞
check the spark plug voltage, as well as fire the individual spark plug.
发动机转速可调节很有用
Being able to set the motor's RPM is really useful,
巡航控制团队需要调用那个函数
the cruise control team is going to need to call that function.
但是他们不懂点火系统如何工作
But, they don't know much about how the ignition system works.
所以让他们调用点燃单个火花塞的函数不合适
It's not a good idea to let them call functions that fire the individual spark plug,
否则引擎会爆炸的
or the engine might explode!
可能吧
Maybe.
API使合适的人接触合适的函数和数据
The API allows the right people access to the right functions and data.
面向对象的编程语言
Object Oriented Programming languages do this by
通过让你规定函数是共有的还是私有的
letting you specify whether functions are public or private.
如果函数是私有的
If a function is marked as 'private',
说明只有那一对象里面的函数才能调用
it means only functions inside that object can call it.
即在这个例子里 只有点火控制对象里的其他函数
So, in this example, only other functions inside of IgnitionControl,
如设置转速函数能点燃火花塞
like the setRPM function, can fire the spark plugs.
另一方面 因为设置转速函数是共有的
On the other hand, because the setRPM function is marked as public,
其他对象如巡航控制可以调用
other objects can call it, like cruise control.
隐藏复杂性并有选择地展示的能力
This ability to hide complexity, and selectively reveal it,
是面向对象编程的本质
is the essence of Object Oriented Programming,
并且这是有力且常用的防止产生过大的复杂程序的方法
and it's a powerful and popular way to tackle building large and complex programs.
你计算机上每一个软件
Pretty much every piece of software on your computer,
游戏机上的游戏
or game running on your console, was built using an
都是用面向对象的编程语言写的 如C++ C# 或 Objective-C
Object Oriented Programming Language,  like C++, C# or Objective-C.
你也许听过 还有Python Java
Other  popular 'OO' languages you may have heard of are Python and Java.
重要一点 代码在编译之前只是文本
It's important to remember that code, before being compiled, is just text.
前面提到的 你可以在记事本或其他老式文字处理器上写代码
As I mentioned earlier, you could write code in Notepad or any old word processor.
有些人确实这样做
Some people do.
但是通常 现在软件开发者使用专门的应用程序写程序
But generally, today's software developers use special-purpose applications
它们集成了许多有用的工具
for writing programs, ones that integrate many useful tools
辅助编写 组织 编译和测试代码
for writing, organizing, compiling and testing code.
因为他们把所需要的放在一起
Because they put everything you need in one place,
叫做集成开发环境IDE
they're called Integrated Development Environments, or IDEs for short.
所有的IDE给写代码提供文本编辑器
All IDEs provide a text editor for writing code, often with useful features
它有着实用的功能例如给代码上色来提高可读性
like automatic color-coding to improve readability.
很多甚至在你打字时检查语法错误 就像是代码的拼写检查
Many even check for syntax errors as you type, like spell check for code.
大程序有许多单独的源文件
Big programs contain lots of individual source files,
所以IDE让程序员能组织和高效地定位
so IDEs allow programmers to organize and efficiently navigate everything.
IDE还内置了编译和运行代码的功能
Also built right into the IDE is the ability to compile and run code.
如果你的程序崩溃了 因为它还在运行中
And if your program crashes, because it's still a work in progress,
IDE可以带你找到崩溃发生的代码行
the IDE can take you back to the line of code where it happened,
通常还能提供额外的信息帮助你查出并修改漏洞
and often provide additional information to help you track down and fix the bug,
这一过程叫做调试
which is a process called debugging.
调试很重要 因为绝大多数程序员花费百分之70到80的时间
This is important because most programmers spend 70 to 80% of their time
测试和调试 而不是写新代码
testing and debugging, not writing new code.
IDE里好的工具可以
Good tools, contained in IDEs, can go a long way
极大帮助程序员预防和发现错误
when it comes to helping programmers prevent and find errors.
许多计算机程序员会很忠心于自己的IDE
Many computer programmers can be pretty loyal to their IDEs though.
不过实话说 VIM很不错 只要你懂如何退出
But let's be honest, VIM is where it's at, providing you know how to quit.
写代码和调试之外 程序员还有一个重要工作
In addition to coding and debugging, another important part of a programmer's job
就是记录说明代码
is documenting their code.
可以用单独的 read me 文件
This can be done in standalone files called 'read me's which tell other programmers
其他程序员浏览之前阅读它的帮助文件
to read that help file before diving in.
也可以在代码内部添加注释
It can also happen right in the code itself with comments.
特殊标记的声明
These are specially-marked statements that the program knows to ignore
在编译时会被忽略
when the code is compiled.
它们帮助程序员理解源代码里每一部分的目的
They exist only to help programmers figure out what's what in the source code.
好的文件说明能帮助程序员
Good documentation helps programmers when they revisit code
当他们隔了很久再次看代码时
they haven't seen for awhile,
对新进的程序员也很重要
but it's also crucial for programmers who are totally new to it.
我要在这里强调
I just want to take a second here and reiterate that it’s THE WORST
别人扔给你一堆没有注释和说明的代码
when someone parachutes a load of uncommented and undocumented code into your lap,
你真的得逐行阅读才能理解代码在干什么 这很糟糕
and you literally have to go line by line to understand what the code is doing.
认真地 别做这样的人
Seriously. Don't be that person.
文件说明也促进代码的重复利用
Documentation also promotes code reuse.
程序员不是一遍遍不停写同样的东西
So, instead of having programmers constantly write the same things over and over,
他们截取他人的代码做自己的事
can track down someone else's code that does what they need.
多亏了文件说明 他们可以把代码移植来
Then, thanks to documentation, they can put it to work in their program,
而不用读那些代码
without ever having to read through the code.
”读文件说明吧“程序员这么说
'Read the docs' as they say.
IDE之外另一个帮助大团队合作完成大工程重要的软件
In addition to IDEs, another important piece of software that helps big teams
版本控制
work collaboratively on big coding projects is called Source Control,
它的英文名source control 也叫 version control 或 revision control
also known as version control or revision control.
通常 苹果和微软这样大软件公司
Most often, at a big software company like Apple or Microsoft,
所有工程的代码储存在中央服务器中 叫做代码仓库
code for projects is stored on centralized servers, called a code repository.
当程序员想编辑一段代码 他们可以从中取出
When a programmer wants to work on a piece of code, they can check it out,
有点像从图书馆借出书
sort of like checking out a book out from a library.
通常IDE里就能完成
Often, this can be done right in an IDE.
然后他们根据自己想法编辑这段代码
Then, they can edit this code all they want on their personal computer,
增加新功能并测试
adding new features and testing if they work.
当程序员确定改变能运行了
When the programmer is confident their changes are working
没有错误了 可以放回仓库了
and there are no loose ends, they can check the code back into the repository,
叫做提交代码 供其他人使用
known as committing code, for everyone else to use.
当一段代码被取出并更新修改了
While a piece of code is checked out, and presumably getting updated or modified,
其他程序员便不管它了
other programmers leave it alone.
这防止了异常冲突和重复工作
This prevents weird conflicts and duplicated work.
这样 几百个程序员可以同时工作
In this way, hundreds of programmers can be simultaneously
取出和存入一段段代码 如此反复搭建巨大的系统
checking in and out pieces of code, iteratively building up huge systems.
重要的是 你不希望别人提交有漏洞的代码
Critically, you don't want someone committing buggy code,
因为其他人或团队可能依赖它
because other people and teams may rely on it.
他们的代码因此可能崩溃 造成混乱和浪费时间
Their code could crash, creating confusion and lost time.
代码的主版本 储存在服务器中
The master version of the code, stored on the server,
必须始终无错误编译和尽量降低漏洞
should always compile without errors and run with minimal bugs.
有时候漏洞会悄悄出现
But sometimes bugs creep in.
幸运的是 版本控制软件记录所有变化 如果漏洞出现了
Fortunately, source control software keeps track of all changes, and if a bug is found,
所有的或一段代码可以回到原来稳定的版本
the whole code, or just a piece, can be rolled back to an earlier, stable version.
它还记录了谁做了每个变化 这样合作者可以
It also keeps track of who made each change, so coworkers can send nasty,
寄邮件骂 不对 帮助和鼓励惹麻烦的人
I mean, helpful and encouraging emails to the offending person.
调试在写代码同时完成
Debugging goes hand in hand with writing code,
而且这往往由一个人或是一个小团队完成
and it's most often done by an individual or small team.
大范围的调试叫做质量保证测试QA
The big picture version of debugging is Quality Assurance testing, or QA.
这是指团队严格的测试一段程序
This is where a team rigorously tests out a piece of software,
努力创造无法预见的可能出差错的情况
attempting to create unforeseen conditions that might trip it up.
基本上 能引出漏洞
Basically, they elicit bugs.
把所有的小问题找出来花费巨大精力
Getting all the wrinkles out is a huge effort, but vital in making sure
但对于保证软件上市前能
the software works as intended for as many users
在假设中很多人和情况下按预期工作 至关重要
in as many situations as imaginable before it ships.
你也许听过测试版
You've probably heard of beta software.
它是软件几乎完成但没有百分百通过测试的版本
This is a version of software that's mostly complete, but not 100% fully tested.
公司有时候会公开发行测试版帮他们找出问题
Companies will sometimes release beta versions to the public to help them identify issues,
这基本就像有了一个免费的QA团队
It's essentially like getting a free QA team.
你可能没听过测试版之前的这个版本
What you don't hear about as much is the version that comes before the beta:
alpha版本
the alpha version.
它通常十分粗糙充满漏洞 只在内部测试
This is usually so rough and buggy, it's only tested internally.
它是冰山的一角
So, that's the tip of the iceberg in terms of the tools, tricks and techniques
背后是使软件工程师能建造大量软件的工具 技巧 技术
that allow software engineers to construct the huge pieces of software
这些软件我们熟知并喜爱 像油管 侠盗猎车5 PPT演示文稿
that we know and love today, like YouTube, Grand Theft Auto 5, and Powerpoint.
正如你想的 那些几百万行的代码
As you might expect, all those millions of lines of code needs
需要严格的处理能力保证以有效速度运行
some serious processing power to run at useful speeds,
所以下一集 我们讨论计算机如何运行这么高速
so next episode we'll be talking about how computers got so incredibly fast.
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
下集见
See you then.